test one two good evening everyone i now call to order this special meeting of lancaster city council for november 20th 2025. a few reminders for everyone at the top of the meeting please take a moment to silence your phones and devices if you have not done so already this meeting and its participants are being recorded tonight is a special meeting of city
council there are no general public comment periods during this meeting but comment will
will be taken during our legislative agenda which is one item comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and must begin with your name and your block of residence for our meeting record to keep time this evening I'll be using the light in front of me it will turn green when your time begins it will blink yellow when there is one minute remaining and blink red when three minutes has been exhausted thank you all in advance for ensuring that we keep equal time for all at the time that the light blinks the speaker will be asked and their comment and now for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the Pledge of Allegiance mr. Harris would you please call the roll of members yes madam president mr. man here mr. Arroyo here mr. Cleese yeah miss Craig here miss Diaz here mr. Hirsch here the president Baker here that will take us to our legislative agenda first and only resolutions we have one administration resolution number 79 mr. Harris if he would read it into the record a resolution of the City Council of the City of Lancaster approving a community benefits agreement by and among LP e o 1 prop Co LLC Greenfield Road owner LLC Harrisburg place owner LLC and the City of Lancaster attached here to as exhibit a and authorizing and directing the appropriate city officials to take any and all actions necessary to implement the same I make a motion to approve second Thank You councillors we have a motion and a second we'll begin our discussion of this resolution we will hear a presentation tonight on this
community benefits agreement we'll begin with mayor Sirachi thank you could I
advance the slide one thank you thank you mr. hand worker tonight well good evening council well much of what you will hear this evening has been shared
with you and the public already tonight is an opportunity to bring it all together I want to thank you for this time and your patience as we work
through the negotiations related to the community benefits agreement I am joined tonight by the city solicitor Barry Handwerker and Chris Delves director of community planning economic development they along with two consultants Gabrielle Weger and Al Yates will review the environmental commitments again the clean energy commitment and the two community benefit funds Barry will also review enforcement provisions contained in the agreement for my part I want to take a few moments to share my perspective much of which I shared at the press conference on Tuesday but I think it bears repeating Lancaster like small cities everywhere has been grappling with aging infrastructure and the changing nature of industry and economic development much of the job and tax generating industrial activity that once powered cities like ours is no longer here during my time in office the UPMC Hospital on College Avenue Kunzler and LSC communications for the formerly RR Donnelly plants all closed each time the city has faced the same challenge how to shape the future of properties that we do not own one tool for shaping that future is zoning zoning establishes where uses are permitted and helps guide the long-term
character of our built environment but zoning alone cannot secure the kinds of community benefits or operational commitments that our residents reasonably
expect in the face of new and emerging industries while acknowledging community concern about needing data center specific zoning regulations and working to create those we simultaneously chose a more proactive path through a community benefits agreement this CBA allowed us to negotiate environmental protections, operational standards, and community investments that go far beyond what zoning can require. In doing so, Lancaster secured commitments that I believe are atypical for data center development anywhere in Pennsylvania. And I just want to put a footnote on that. I've spent a lot of time looking at where data centers are being proposed throughout Pennsylvania. They are on hundreds of acres of greenfields that in some cases were previously zoned for housing. What we're talking about tonight are two industrial properties totaling over 2 million square feet they have been printing operations and prior to that the Schick plant was located on Greenfield Road they have infrastructure for high energy use although of course not as high as a data center they have
train spurs that are connected to them and I just felt like I needed to say because not everybody knows where they are and they are in the periphery of the
city comprised of a lot of paved and parking lots with I don't know they can park about 800 cars each so while the city continues to work through the legal requirements to adopt amendments to its zoning ordinance related to data centers if approved by council this CBA confirms that the proposed zoning ordinance will not apply to these two sites at 216 greenfield road and 1375 harrisburg pike the owners will however still be required to comply with all other applicable land development and use laws ordinances and processes including receiving land development approval and applying for and receiving necessary building permits and certificates of occupancy in no way should the cba be construed as a replacement for the zoning text amendment or a signal that that work should stop to the contrary it is the cba and the proposed zoning ordinance taken together that protect our environment and quality of life as well as make investments directly in lancaster lancaster city's sustainability goals and its future economic development once again lancaster finds itself on the vanguard of the issues defining this moment in history as we navigate an era of rapid technological advancement the cba and the proposed zoning ordinance continue to position lancaster as a leader punching above our weight class while staying true to our community values i hope you will agree and with that i will turn it over to mr handwerger to begin the review of the environmental commitments embedded in the cba mr handwerger thank you mayor good evening council mr delfs is joining me is we're really going to tag team a bit on this and give you as much perspective as we can on what's in the agreement to start you probably heard a bunch of names in that resolution that you haven't heard in these chambers before relating to the development of this property or these properties i thought it would be helpful to explain the ownership a little bit and what's happened here it is very typical for large developments for real estate developments business developments to create new entities that will hold either the single business or single asset that is the subject of that business and that's what's happened here. We have two properties with three owners so now you say wait a minute what's
going on? So we'll go through that a little bit. The Harrisburg Pike property is owned by one owner and that's the Harrisburg Place Owner LLC, a limited liability company that was formed to own and hold that property. The Greenfield
property was made the subject of a condominium. A declaration of condominium was filed by the owner which essentially creates two ownership units. Those two ownership units are the other two
parties that we heard in that resolution. LPE 0 Prop Co 1 LLC and Greenfield Road Owner LLC.
Each of those is intended to own one of the two buildings that will be built on
that property. LPE being the first one and Greenfield being the second. So we have three parties we haven't heard about before that were formed by the party you have heard about, the developers of this property, that now own these two sites and have created
entities to hold what is anticipated to be three buildings. You've heard much discussion
over the past months about environmental performance commitments. This agreement
now contains them and contains the substance of those agreements. First the water maximum of 20,000 gallons per day per campus and by campus now we're
referring to each of the two properties remembering that there's going to be two
buildings on one and one building on the other but regardless of whether it's two buildings or one building in either of those situations neither of those properties the combination of the two buildings on the one and the one building on the other will utilize more than 20 gallons per day of water and just to note the previous usage from some of the entities the mayor mentioned Donnelly LSC I mean they were in the 100 to 125 thousand gallons per day range in
the type of use they had there and that's because there's a closed loop
cooling system which is being utilized and again there's you'll hear more about some of the systems but there's no additional chemicals being applied to that so noise if you recall the merit indicated in previous conversations with council that the city wanted to review the existing noise study and then determine what noise was going to be happening make sure it was controlled
this agreement does a couple of things it lays out what the noise requirements
are as to not create noise that exceeds the ambient level that already exists at the receiving properties and we're gonna have an expert tell you about that we We did hire somebody to review their study, and that individual not only reviewed it but
helped negotiate and re-craft language that allows for some additional noise testing to be done as we go forward. So Gabriel Weger is the acoustics and noise control lead for Burns & McDonnell, an international engineering company. I'd like to bring him into the meeting now.
He's going to be appearing by teams, and he's going to talk to you a little bit about the noise study and what's contained in section 3.1 of the ordinance go through
a little bit of background on data center acoustics and and what we have in the CBA and what the the owners of the data center project are going to be held to moving forward over the past several years and I've helped do the acoustic design for more than 40 data center projects both in pre-construction acoustic modeling to predict future operational sound levels and testing once the data centers are built to confirm that those data centers met their limits for their respective jurisdictions. Major noise sources when it comes to data centers are both the cooling equipment as well as the emergency generators. During normal operation, the cooling equipment and compressors are the main source of noise. The generators will also emit noise, but only during the readiness testing and emergency operations, which are the readiness testing would only be done during daytime hours, not on weekends or holidays. And the emergency operations would be few and far between when the data center lost power. The city ordinance prohibits noise disturbances
within the city, but it doesn't establish a set decibel level
that would constitute a disturbance. So, as part of the CBA, we've included performance commitments for the owners of the AI Hub to reduce the likelihood of future noise disturbances from the project. The owners have hired Thornton Tomasetti, a reputable data center acoustics firm to complete preliminary environmental noise review of the projects. And as part of that study, they modeled the operation of the data centers. They adequately addressed the noise generating components of the project. And what we did in working with the owners, the city and myself added a few requirements that we think are adequate to protect the noise sense of areas near the projects from additional noise pollution. Section 3.1 of the Community Benefits Agreement is what we drafted, and this agreement establishes that the owners cannot transmit any project-generated noise to the surrounding noise sense of areas of each project exceeding the existing ambient sound levels. So what they're going to be doing next is taking ambient sound levels at each of those noise-sensitive areas surrounding the project, and that will be what sets the limit for the project moving forward so that we have a sound level that they can be held to, that they will have to test once the project is operational to confirm that they met those ambient sound levels. The way the ambient sound levels are going to be established
is through daytime and nighttime monitoring
of the existing ambient sound levels. the lowest one-hour equivalent sound level measured during daytime, which would be their limit for generator readiness testing in normal operations, and then the nighttime limit for the lowest one hour
during nighttime hours for just the normal operations,
where they wouldn't be doing generator readiness testing. The owner's noise consultant is in the process of completing that additional ambient survey. And once that final sound study is complete, my team at Burns & McDonnell and the city will review the study that they provide
ensure the acoustic design beats the requirements of the cba thank you gabe uh madam president if council would like to ask gabe questions i'd certainly be uh and have him entertain them thank you i know i appreciate that we have limited time with our experts and appreciate their insight so just briefly counsel if you have noise specific questions for mr wenger
this would be the appropriate time to take them any council questions on noise
counts president council Hirsch thank you Gabriel my question is around the
the lowest one-hour equivalent sound level can you just explain what exactly that means because I think I kind of understand it but I think it would benefit all of us to understand what uh is meant by the lowest one hour equivalent sound level absolutely and so what you get in these environments is you have a mix of constant noise in an area as well as fluctuating sound levels that might be associated with increases in traffic flow to the area maybe a train passing by these various intermittent noise sources that change the ambient environment at the time those noise sources are present so So, what we're requiring the applicant to do is to take ambient measurements and take the lowest one-hour average sound level during both daytime and nighttime hours. So, you may have loud environments during rush hour traffic in the morning and evening.
We don't want to use those to set the limit for the project. What we want to do is take the lowest average sound level that might happen at 2 a.m. or at 2 p.m.
when there's not much traffic or activity going on and ensure that that is the ambient sound level that they're using for their design. This doesn't mean that the data center would never be audible. It just ensures that the data center noise that's generated is in line with the lowest ambient environment that currently exists in those areas. So, they wouldn't have a significant change to the existing noise levels in the area. Brett Redfearn Thank you.
Jennifer Marietta- Thank you, Counselor Hirsch.
Counselors, anything additional? Counselor Craig. Hi, Gabriel. This is Counselor Craig speaking.
You mentioned that once the work is done, that it would be tested, the levels of noise would be tested. Who's going to be doing the testing?
Don't know that that has been established.
Typically, you would hire a third-party consultant to do the testing in line with standard industry practices.
I don't believe that that consultant has been chosen at this time It wouldn't be the owner doing their own testing with a cell phone. You would be expected to have a reputable firm doing the testing But there's numbers of acoustic consultants out there that would be qualified to do this testing
Okay. Thank you. Thank you. Council Craig
counselor med Thank You council president and Thank You Gabriel for answering our questions this evening
My question was around the generator testing occurring only during daytime hours and not on Sundays or federal holidays. Is this consistent with other projects you have seen? Because this does seem like a significant benefit for the city.
I would say that it is common.
If you don't have a community benefits agreement that clearly establishes that, Many of local sound level requirements may just say you're limited to 50 dBA during daytime hours,
and they're not going to prevent you from testing on a Saturday if you're below that threshold.
I have seen ordinances specific to data centers that do call this out,
but I wouldn't say that it is unanimous for all noise ordinances that are drafted specific to data centers.
I've seen it both ways. So this does add an added benefit that that testing would not take place on weekends or holidays Thank you, and that concludes my questions madam president. Thank you Mr. Hamburger Thank You Gabriel your your time and attention is much appreciated and should this project move forward I look forward to working with you as the studies get completed I also note as we deal with noise that as with a number of other items We'll note later a noise mitigation plan has to be provided for each building which will in part detail one of the questions asked here which is who would be doing the testing and when so then we move to air quality and has been has been set forth here in chambers in the past the requirements in the agreement haven't really changed from what's been announced which is that the owners need to comply with all state and federal requirements and that there they need to comply with the permitting requirements and the things put in that permit by DEP which include for the current Greenfield property using very high-level technology to date. As with Noyes, the city employed an outside consultant to review the filings that had been made for the permit by Carissa, the state regulations, the equipment and plans that had been submitted related to air emissions and
to guide us on what what the state was doing with what the permit requirements were and to again help assist in drafting any appropriate language for
air quality I note that mr. Yates from the armed group LLC was going to join us momentarily assisted greatly in helping us to expand some of the things we wanted to have included as required documents to be provided, including their spill prevention control and countermeasures and spill prevention response plans. But Mr. Yates is an engineer with the Arm Group LLC, which is a central Pennsylvania firm that does national work, again, in the areas of specialty that we're dealing with here. And with that, I'll ask Mr. Yates to talk to counsel a bit about the DEP process, the rules and regulations, and the rather strong requirements
that are actually in the permit that is under review currently. So with that, welcome, Al. Okay, thank you. My name is Al Yates. I'm a professional engineer at Arm Group. I have over 25 years of experience in air quality permitting in addition to
design and permitting of numerous industrial facilities arm was retained to evaluate the air emissions and air quality permit applications for the two proposed data center facilities to be located at 216 greenfield road and 1375 harrisburg pike currently only the 216 greenfield road air quality permit application has been submitted to the pennsylvania department of environmental protection. That's the PADEP. It is my understanding that the air quality permit application for the second site, the 1375 Harrisburg Pike facility, will be submitted at a later date. So as far as air permitting goes, the power supply for data centers is pretty much a belts and suspenders approach. First is drawing power off the electric grid. If there's some interruption in that there's a secondary backup which is the battery backup system and third if if all those uh aren't available it's the backup emergency generators to supply power to the data centers based on arms review the emergency generators are going to be the sole source of air emissions that require air quality permitting at this facility the emergency generators are intended to be operated at the site as needed during times of utility power outages maintenance and readiness testing electrical infrastructure maintenance or what a reasonable
probability of utility power outage exists the padp has issued a draft airplane approval permit that limits the operation both for emergency and non-emergency use of each emergency engine
to 100 hours per year based on any consecutive 12-month period calculating monthly so it's basically a rolling uh calculation so an airplane approval is the initial air permit that authorizes the construction and installation of air emission sources and their air emissions controls as well as temporary operation usually for a period of 180 days although extensions may be granted following this period the padp will issue an operating permit for these sources the operating permit will incorporate the air emissions controls and represent the airplane approval permit so basically the airplane approval permit is for the initial installation of the sources and kind of a shakedown period and then the operating permit is issued afterwards once the system is up and up and running so in reviewing the timeline for the permit applications the developers consultant all four which is a well-recognized uh air permitting company and consultant prepared
and submitted an airplane approval application for the proposed 216 greenfield road facility to the padp on behalf of the data center this application was submitted to the padp on may 14
2025 the initial application proposed 164 diesel fired emergency generators but this number was subsequently increased to 176. on june 12th the city of lancaster provided comments on the plan approval application to the padp on november 3rd the padp provided the draft plan approval permit
and permit review memo to the city of lancaster as part of the permit review memo the padp did respond to all the city of lancaster comments the notice for the draft plan approval permit was published in the pa bulletin on november 15th and then a 30-day public comment period on the draft permit began on that date once the 30-day period has expired the padp will review any comments that are received and then make a final determination on the issuance of the era plan approval permit arm reviewed the proposed air emissions calculations contained within the permit application and compared the proposed emissions air emissions controls to both state and federal air quality standards the following air emissions controls requirements were proposed
by the developer to meet the air emissions regulations including best available technology
which is kind of the state of the practice it's also called bat standard the proposed potential
air emissions are below major source thresholds therefore the greenfield road facility is not subject to non-attainment new source review and prevention of significant deterioration standards basically what that means is they're not a major source which would require a federal air permit this is also called a title v permit they are a minor source which requires a state-only permit which is issued through the padp the emergency generator engines are subject to tier 2 emission standards what that means is uh they'll basically generate less regulated air emissions than some of the older engines that are out there certified tier 2 engines are proposed and
required in the draft permit they're required to use ultra low sulfur diesel fuel to power the emergency generators that is a requirement the requirement for that is having less than 15
parts per million of sulfur sulfur is a component of sulfur dioxides that are a byproduct of
combustion and internal combustion engines they're required to limit the hours of operation to 100
hours per year on a rolling basis and they agreed to install emissions controls which are kind of state of the state of the practice on these engines they're installing selective catalytic selective catalytic reduction system also called scr which also has an integrated catalyzed diesel particulate filter per the manufacturer's specifications this system will achieve achieve a reduction of about 94 percent for nitrogen oxides about 70 percent for carbon monoxide about 50 percent for volatile organic compounds and about 70 percent for filterable particulate matter the combination of the tier 2 engines the use of the ultra low sulfur diesel fuel limits of 100 hours per year on engine running time and the air emissions controls combined to keep the proposed air emissions below the major source or federal permit threshold consequently this application is being approved as a minor permit issued by the state rather than a major permit based on arms review the 216 greenfield road data center airplane approval application was complete and meets the applicable state and federal air quality standards it is arm's opinion that the padp was acting within its authority by issuing the draft airplane approval for those proposed operations as part of my review i also reviewed the community benefits agreement and specifically in this case section 3.2 which covers uh the air emissions um and found that to be consistent with uh what was being proposed in the air uh airplane approval permit uh with some additional information that the data center will comply with all federal and state laws uh and there's uh with with air permitting there's uh very exacting laws that uh and regulations that are required to uh to comply with uh they specifically mentioned using the selective catalytic reduction system and all other systems required by this approved by the city and state and including a spill prevention control and countermeasures plan and a spill prevention response plan which are important because these generators have large diesel fuel tanks and it's important to have a spill control plans to adequately manage them okay so that concludes my my review thank you al uh madam president again if there are questions from council i'm sure al would be more than happy to answer them thank you very much mr yates appreciate your expertise i do have a question for you um so this this this really ensures that the permit process is going through and all of these, you know, specifications. But can you speak to how the state DEP monitors these permits ongoing? Michael Heaney- Yes. So, because, so this would be considered a synthetic minor permit. So, once they, so I guess first I'll talk about the current permit that they're applying for, is the plan approval permit they have a about a 30-page permit document that's issued to them that they have to which is full of conditions that they have to comply with one of them is monitoring conditions so they have to monitor that emissions control system they have to monitor the temperature
of it the pressure of it that the urea within it is functioning correctly and what that does
is basically when you combine the urea at at the appropriate temperature with the exhaust gases it converts the nitrogen oxides into harmless nitrogen gas and water so there's a number of requirements on uh upkeep and making sure that it's the not only the engines are operating appropriately and maintained appropriately but that the emissions controls are operating correctly uh there's requirements to uh record the the hours that the system is used and whether it's used in as a as a backup power source or whether it's for testing um there's uh about three pages worth of requirements and conditions they have uh pages eight through 18 through 20 in their draft uh
airplane permit approval uh that they have to record and uh and submit or keep on site for the
padp to uh if uh when they inspect the facility once they go to get their operating permit because
they're a synthetic uh also the padp will send out inspectors periodically to review not only the paperwork but their operations um and the pad people also certainly respond to any uh any
complaints as well great thank you very much other members of council questions for mr yates counselor med uh thank you council president uh and thank you for uh taking our questions this evening uh my question was um in regards to your review of the uh community benefits agreement uh could Could you just once again reemphasize how you found it was consistent with what was proposed in the plan approval permit and applicable to the state and federal laws? so the so the community benefits agreement specifically states that the uh uh ai hub
shall comply with all federal and state laws which which includes the clean air act which is what is
the basis of the airplane approval permit and the subsequent operate airplane or air operating
permit that they will receive once the uh emergency generators and emissions air emissions
controls have been installed um they also agreed to provide copies of all the permits that they received uh to to the city uh so that the so that the city can verify that they uh have installed what they said they're going to install and uh that they're complying with uh with what they
with with what they said they would install um they agreed specifically to install the selective
catalytic reduction system uh which is truly critical to uh making sure that the the air emissions are as agreed to in the airplane approval document um the airplane approval itself uh is is basically uh a written set of instructions that the facility is required to comply with uh under threat of of enforcement action and removal of their permit and heavy heavy fines um and then the inclusion of the the spill plans uh also make sure that they are uh that they have a system in place to address any uh any spills or leaks and that the uh the substantial amount of diesel fuel tanks are properly installed and have properly have secondary containment and emergency response set up in case there is any issue thank you and that concludes my questions thank you additional questions for mr yates from council mr hanberger
Thank you, Al. We'll move forward with the remainder of the presentation.
We're going to move on to the next of the environmental commitments, and maybe the trickiest one to describe, but in part maybe the most significant for us here this evening. Energy. There is an absolute commitment to have 100 percent clean energy applied to these two properties. that being said the the agreement acknowledges the market that exists or may exist or may not exist as time goes on with respect to clean energy as we're all aware the federal administration is sort of had moving goalposts in terms of its energy policies and that could change during the term of this clearly during the term of this agreement. So at the outset, they can't start operating unless they have 100 percent clean energy sources at a time of operation. We will not be issuing a certificate, a permanent certificate of occupancy, unless they have certified that. Or they do have an option at any time throughout the course of the agreement to present 10-year power purchase agreement signed by their tenants now remember we talked a little bit about three buildings and each one being separately owned and separately operated the expectation and business plan is for them to lease each building to one tenant it may be the same tenant in all three but each each building will have a separate lease with the goal being a single tenant for that building those leases are anticipated to be triple net meaning that basically all of the responsibilities of ownership and occupancy of the building are borne by the tenant rather than the owner. So if the tenant can produce a 10-year contract for either 100 percent clean energy between 180 or 160, their obligations for clean energy under the agreement will be met. There's some disincentives built into the agreement for them producing contracts for less than 100%. The disincentives are payments to a fund, Mr. Delfts will talk about a little later, a sustainability fund of the city. So we'll talk a little bit about those payments. The payments are going to be secured in part by a letter of credit. The payments, if you are, and because we have three buildings not
for the numbers equate to a little bit differently. What they really equate to is totals per campus
broken up by building. But if a building, Building 1 or Building 2, which is on the Greenfield site, produces a contract at any time that says we've got 10 years of guaranteed 100 percent clean energy, then they've met their commitment to operate under that contract.
At the end of that contract, their obligations under this agreement regarding clean energy
have been solved, but they have satisfied their clean energy commitments by doing so. If they haven't presented that or one of the other contracts, they have an obligation to be at 100 percent.
If they present a contract of a 10-year power purchase agreement for less than 100 but over 80 percent, that would have to be coupled with a payment in the amount of $2.5 million
the city's sustainability fund. Again, it's the 10-year contract and the payment. Both have to be made, in which case their obligation is met. If they haven't made both of those, so if they haven't made the payment or they haven't produced the 10-year contract, then they're under an ongoing obligation to be at 100% clean energy. Same thing with the first property and the second property, both on the Greenfield site. If they're between 60 percent and 80 percent, so again the floor here being 60, and they produce a 10-year contract for clean energy that's somewhere in that range, they can do so and end their commitments along with the making of a five million dollar payment. Building three, the property on Harrisburg Pike, just take those payments and multiply them by two it's five million dollars for eighty to a hundred and ten million dollars for sixty to eighty these payments at the outset are secured by a letter of credit in the amount of ten million dollars that letter of credit will be reduced when they make a payment so they make a payment so they bought they've essentially bought a ten-year power
our purchase agreement, submitted that, and they make a payment to the city, then the collateral gets reduced. The letter of credit would get reduced by the corresponding amount of the payment,
$2.5 million, $5 million, or $10 million. Until all three buildings have either submitted contracts for 10 years or the term of the agreement expires, whichever occurs first, the letter of credit must remain at a minimum of $5 million. So if a payment, if due to payments it falls below $5 million, they need to reestablish a higher amount of collateral. Now that still means there might be a payment theoretically that would need to be made that isn't secured. We'll talk about enforcement later on, but the reality here is, remember I talked about two things that have to be done the payment has to be made and and the 10-year contract has to be submitted both in order for their commitment not to have a hundred percent to be released and we'll talk about enforcement if they don't meet their commitments as a very strong provision of this agreement it's also important to note that initially but before they get issued their final certificate of occupancy from the city, they will either need to certify that for the then upcoming year they're operating at 100% clean energy or have submitted one of these four certificates, a certificate of a 10-year commitment to 100%, a certificate of, I'm sorry, three certificates, a certificate of 10 years at 80 to 100, or a certificate of 10 years at 60 to 80. So they can't start operating
if they're not in compliance to begin with please Chris Barry's gonna let me jump in here for a moment I just wanted to zoom out a little bit and talk about very briefly I know that there was a lot of complexity there and I wanted to just
speak Brett briefly about the intention behind that whole approach both the owner and operator of the site plus the city are committed and intend to achieve a hundred percent clean energy that that was the primary objective of the negotiations however part of the tricky element here was the timing of the power
purchase agreements the operators or the tenants who occupy these buildings will not be making purchases of the power probably a long-term purchase until a
later time so we had to get creative and figure out how do we set up a safeguard in the event that a hundred percent clean energy cannot be attained again there is a strong commitment on all sides to reach that 100% but the city
felt that we had to have additional requirements in place disincentives and
accountability provisions to help ensure we get there thank you Chris the agreement contains 13 other significant commitments and these are all related to the use of the property they include and many of them as we'll see when we get to the next slide require submission of plans which must be approved by the city
but they they include the requirements for landscaping in tree canopy buffering
and screening with setbacks built in of 100 feet and 50 feet lighting is actually a rather significant provision here the city does not currently have any dark sky provisions in its ordinances and the owners are committed
to developing a lighting plan that's consistent with the core principles of the international dark sky standards five core principles flow into that that
is something that we did not have legislatively in any way shape or form currently and as we move through some of our rewrites of the saldo and zoning ordinance as part of the inconsistency with the comp plan those are going to be things that are going to be on the table at that point it requires a thermal heat mitigation plan and requirements for thermal heat mitigation specific provisions regarding cooling systems chillers and generators specific specific commitments regarding their committed stormwater usage climate resiliency how they're going to build their buildings in a healthy way and restoration following construction. Requirements regarding fencing that are consistent with the zoning ordinance but go beyond it. Provisions regarding emergency management. So not only do they have to have an emergency management plan, they have to train our staff at their cost on how to make sure that we can handle the unique facilities that are going to be inside these buildings. And if a emergency, a fire emergency exceeds $25,000, they're responsible for that excessive cost. Provisions regarding noise testing. This is noise testing outside of what Gabe talked about. So following commencement of operations, if they're receiving complaints and we request, we need to have you test to see what's going on here. They have agreed to noise testing no more than once every couple of years because of the timing of it but they have agreed to do so on a complaint basis they have a requirement to maintain a website and to create a complaint process on that website to post relevant information on the website there are significant hiring policies that have been put in place here and an annual reporting
requirement regarding their energy usage for the previous year and the sources of
it. And Chris, did you ever want to add anything there? Thanks, Barry. Mostly, I just wanted to talk about these particular elements as a group. I think Barry called out the highlights on each of these bullets. I wanted to draw this back to the mayor's opening remarks when she talked about
the community benefits agreement and how that works in tandem with the proposed zoning amendment.
don't want to muddy the waters and talk about the zoning amendment too much right now but I think it's important to give credit to the work of staff and City Council and the City Planning Commission who have already reviewed and
provided feedback on a proposed zoning amendment a lot of the good work that
happened on that zoning amendment related to these more classic topics were actually pulled into the community benefits agreement and reflected here so
the most the most classic example is probably buffering and screening that's
something that you see in a lot of different types of zoning districts to protect particularly commercial and manufacturing uses in addition to that we have things in the CBA that we don't typically address in zoning like the
lighting and again Barry mentioned that the the information in the community benefits agreement related to lighting requires that the owner and operator
meet basically develop a plan in accordance with the principles of the international dark sky standards so we have several things here that both mirror the zoning amendment and in many cases go beyond the zoning amendment as well thank you Chris and as I noted there are a number of plans that are required to be filed with the city and that must be approved by the city and many of them have to be approved have to be prepared by qualified experts they include an emergency management plan e waste management plan which is basically the disposal of e waste landscaping plans lighting plan local hiring plan
and noise mitigation plan for each building and these are all related to
each building by the way and with that Chris is going to talk a little bit about the two funds and the two sizable contributions into each of those funds that will be made great Thank You Barry and I'm sorry City Council I didn't say hello and I first spoke earlier it's it's nice to see you all we're gonna change gears a little bit here and talk about a part of the community benefits
agreement that is different in addition to the environmental and quality of life commitments as I think you've heard me say on a number of other occasions the vast majority of time that we spent in negotiations really focused upon the environmental commitments and all the performance standards that we just spoke about in particular those big topics related to noise and water and and energy. In addition to that, early in the negotiating process, Carissa Technology Parks did indicate that they were interested in making investments, financial contributions into the community, particularly those that were logically related to the development of a data center and AI hub here in Lancaster. We actually, despite that offer early on,
actually tabled that for most of the negotiations and came back to it in at
the end after we had gotten to where we needed to be with the environmental commitments after that point we had a great deal of back and forth with the Carissa Technology Parks team and ultimately what we landed on is that CTP will contribute a definitive amount of 20 million dollars under the terms of
community benefits agreement there will be two funds that will be established to contain to contain those funds first of all ten million dollars will be placed into an economic development fund and that fund will be managed by the Lancaster County Community Foundation the Lancaster Economic Development Company will also have a special role related to that particular fund as they will serve to lead the creation of a plan that will help determine how to
deploy those funds and the idea there is that we really want to have a strategic approach to make sure that we're getting the maximum benefit out of those out of
those funds secondly the the additional 10 million dollars will be placed into a sustainable development and clean energy fund and that will be managed by the City of Lancaster administration both I think it's important to say that there's
work that needs to be done after establishing both of these funds to
determine exactly which projects and programs we're going to use the funding
for I spoke a little bit just about the economic development fund looking at the
sustainability fund our roadmap there will primarily be the climate action
plan and our comprehensive plan our future Lancaster we have talked
internally about some possible priorities for this this particular fund but again no decisions have been made just wanted to share some of these ideas with you for illustrative purposes one of the things that we have talked about is solar energy generation at or for city facilities we've discussed financial support for other renewable energy projects also concept of providing renewable energy or energy efficiency improvements in Lancaster City homes this could also include park and or open space investments it could include expansion the urban tree canopy to meet city goals there's also an action in the comprehensive plan related to composting facilities equipment or operations and then finally green infrastructure to aid and stormwater habitat and air quality benefits I do want to caution us that as we as we get into the process of deciding about these funds I think we really are looking more for quality than quantity I think especially if we're going to be seeking
impact in the in the renewable energy field we may end up deciding that the highest and best use is in a single project or two or three projects as
opposed to that whole list that I that I read these are all just ideas and Chris if I may just just a reminder that remember we talked about the disincentive payments if made to get it with a 10-year commitment those disincentive payments would be added to this sustainable development and clean energy fund they would not be in they would not be in place of this 10 million they would be in addition to it and they would be managed again by the city for these same purposes
they would be part of the same fund and therefore limited to these purposes so this would not be general fund money that can be used for anything under the agreement it is clear that these will have to be used for the purposes mr delft's discussed thank you barry i'd like to go into
you a little more detail about the payment structure for these financial contributions first and foremost it's important to to say that these financial contributions to the city and to the Lancaster County Community Foundation will be phased there's two dates that are or two triggers that I should say that are identified in the community benefits agreement that's important for us to note here one is the construction financing date and the second is the commencement
of operations and please think about this according to each building so that milestone the financing date and the commencement of operations would be broken out according to
each building as you can see here in the table there would be a financial contribution to the the economic fund economic development fund of 2.5 million dollars when building one construction financing is closed that would be the same for the
sustainability fund 2.5 million also at that particular point in time then once
building the operations of building one begins there would be an additional 2.5 million dollars that that goes into both funds the same thing occurs for building
two it's 2.5 million into each fund at construction financing and then again in at the start of operations if I've done my math correctly in the table that all
adds up 10 million into each fund and 20 million ultimate overall in total there is an asterisk an asterisk next to the first 2.5 million just wanted to note there that there will be a contribution of $250,000 up front so that the
planning related to the economic development fund can get started early
and that we can spend about 12 months or so on that process to help us determine how to allocate the funds. And I'll jump in here a little bit so these these payments these 20 million dollars of payments are secured in full by a
letter of credit in the amount of 20 million dollars so there will be a
letter of credit that has to be issued by a federally insured bank or other financial institution satisfactory to the city securing the payments and again as payments are made they would reduce reduce the amount of the collateral reduce the letter of credit which is which is a fairly typical financing provision it's actually fairly typical in our land development processes when public improvements but they will be fully secured so again the concept of well we've got this entity that was formed just to hold this property and the agreement says you know we that the property is really the only collateral
that's not actually true the letter of credit is the real collateral what the agreement is really saying is that we have to if we get it if we have to sue
them for a payment which we will not because it's secured by collateral we would have a judgment that we could execute against the property and not against the individuals or the entity itself so that's a provision that's in the agreement it's fairly standard in these types of transactions to try to build that that's how they quite frankly get the equity investments that are needed to do these types of projects with that we'll move into it land use approvals and again Chris will take back over I'm sorry council president may ask question yes mr. hamburger it was mentioned buildings 1 and building 2 can you clarify that these payments are going to be done prior to any potential development and built before building 3 so that's assuming that the projects all get constructed in that order so this agreement is all contingent with respect
to each building on it receiving all of its final zoning building land
development building permits legislation being resolved etc litigation being resolved so the presumptive schedule would be that yes but the letter of
credit secures all three buildings regardless of what order there there's
no requirement of order each building each payment is triggered based on when that building gets gets to construction financing and or goes into operations so
the dates are by building they're not necessarily by any plan or land
development plan process yeah and when we refer to buildings one and two the expectation is those buildings are for the greenfield site we're referring to those as the buildings on the greenfield site as a way of describing them not in any particular order although there is really an order the one we're referring
to is building number one is essentially what you see being worked on now which was the demolition of the existing facility and now the preparation for it
to be reconstructed building two would be the construction of a new building once land
development approval is received on that and then building three we were just using that to keep building numbers in place would be the the only building on the harrisburg pike property got it thank you for that clarification thank you certainly thanks barry and you had mentioned building number two the second building on the greenfield road site so that's a perfect segue to come back to the land use approvals and just say a few words about that as barry mentioned
the demolition and foundation work has started on greenfield road building one we also received about a month ago the land development application for greenfield road building number two that application is currently under review by a number of our technical staff within the city We don't have a definitive timeline tonight for the submission of the land development application for the Harrisburg Pike site, but we have been told by the development and construction team that that will be coming shortly.
I did want to try to make a link again briefly to the zoning work that is happening. the mayor mentioned in her remarks at the outset that by signing this
agreement we do want to be clear that the city agrees that the uses at these two sites at 216 Greenfield Road and 1375 Harrisburg Pike are permitted under the current zoning ordinances Chris let me just jump in there and one thing to note there there is a caveat to that which is that the land development plans
have already been submitted for building number two but for Harrisburg Pike that
That allowance of the new ordinance not applying, any new ordinance not applying, only exists for two years. So if they don't file a land development plan within two years, then whatever legislation is in place at that time would apply. Great. Thank you, Barry, for the clarification. Yeah, I do think that's a very important piece of understanding how all of this goes together. The land development application and process for any major site, whether it's a data center, another commercial entity, mixed-use housing development, as many of you know, the land development process is very detailed, and it takes a fair amount of time to make sure that the developer, in concert with city staff, are getting the site design right and that it is complying with all our requirements. relevant ordinances and those relevant ordinances are the subdivision and land development ordinance stormwater ordinance right-of-way ordinance etc there are others that apply as well um and that
actually kind of leads us to that last bullet there that uh regardless of this cba all of those
other laws that we typically apply to projects of this uh this nature are still in place and those processes all remain in effect so we are already taking a careful look at Greenfield Road building number two and the site plans that are associated with that building so now we'll move to a discussion about what happens if they don't comply and it you know from my perspective I've been practicing law for for 35 years now and the one thing I'll note is that law contracts and ordinances laws are both written under a similar principle and that is that reasonable people will comply with the written rule what happens when people aren't reasonable typically you find them or you penalize them by making pay you you money or you sue them to pay you money for your damages think about all the types of cases that we have out there where people are being sued or judgments are being sought and that is a possibility but what we've done with this agreement and what the developers have done is given us a much stronger
means of enforcement two things payments so we talked about the 20 million
dollars of payments to the two funds they're secured in whole by a letter of credit. This is not like a mortgage where you have to issue execution and file a mortgage relief. Letter of credit is a far more fluid and far stronger piece of collateral. If they default, we give them notice that they've defaulted. It's 10 days under this agreement. They don't comply. We call the bank. We write the bank a letter. We tell them there's been a default, and they write us a check. We're covered on payments. What about all their other commitments? Well, typically in most civil matters, if you breach a contract, you can sue and say you breached the contract and we want to be paid for our damages. Well, in this particular case, these commitments were so significant to the city that we insisted that that's not adequate remedy for us. There isn't an amount of money that will replace the clean energy you promised to provide. There isn't an amount of money sufficient to solve the noise problem you promised to prevent. There isn't an amount of money necessary to solve the fact that you're not complying with your state permits for air emissions. So what do we do? We've built into this agreement their promise and agreement that those provisions, there is no adequate remedy at law. And what that means is that monetary damages will not suffice and that they've agreed that
monetary damages will not suffice. And that therefore, when we go to court, we can ask the court to utilize its equitable powers, which are far stronger than its legal powers. And those powers are the powers to compel performance, stop somebody from performing, or enter other
appropriate equitable relief. In this case, that power is as broad as shutting down operations of an operate of a data center that will be doing a lot of work for a lot of people costing a lot of money and so the strongest means of enforcement here is our ability to ask a court to shut them down and that's the enforcement power we have and that's not always given and typically not given except in extreme circumstances for contractual matters so that's that's the enforcement and the other enforcement mechanisms are sort of self-imposed in here you know we have the right to approve those plans I mentioned right so that's our approval we have the right to you know seek testing noise testing if the complaints are made so there there are remedies built in throughout and and what that speaks to is the commitment of the owners to comply with the commitments
they've made and and so I'm encouraged and having done number of contracts and
number of large contracts for the city this is not a remedy that's typical this cut this this agreement does in fact provide pretty significant powers and enforcement abilities to the city yes it involves courts can't change that there's no way to stop the fact that we're gonna have to have potentially a fight over whether a default occurred but once the court agrees that a default has occurred their powers the courts powers are very very great and so from the standpoint of enforcement you can't get much stronger you've collateralized your monetary payments you've hedged against failure to comply or desire to sort of skirt the boundaries by the plan submission requirements themselves so
from that perspective from my perspective as the city solicitor I feel
comfortable that the city is protected again as to the commitments that are made in this agreement and with that mr. Delce and I will conclude our presentation thank you very much at this time I'm going to open it up for council discussion I do have a couple of questions and things I want to talk through I'll begin and then I'll go to other members of council I want to start by saying that I appreciate the level of detail in this agreement and also the
fact that many of the environmental performance commitments were given to
Council almost a month ago and because they are in my mind primary to this discussion and I appreciate that the specific environmental and quality of life concerns that that we wish to prioritize have been prioritized in this process so thank you for that and thank you for the level of detail in explaining them as well I do want to go back to the economic development fund director Delphs if you could speak to the makeup of the committee that would guide that work at the Community Foundation level who who guides that work president vacate thank you for the question I realized we already spent a lot of time on so much detail and I did skip skip over a little bit of detail so it gives me an opportunity to come back here and just speak a little bit about
at a high level the purpose of the fund and really what we thought about in creating this fund is wanting to ensure that these that the funds are used to promote the economic vitality of Lancaster City first and foremost and
really to foster economic mobility and success of residents in Lancaster City and specifically again we haven't made any determined specific determinations
yet about projects and programs but we do think we know about areas of focus or
areas of need and uses general uses of this fund could include projects and programs that enhance local business development technical assistance for local businesses and workforce development in particular we we We understand that there are larger economic forces at play that sit behind the arrival
of data centers in Lancaster City and in other areas throughout Pennsylvania and throughout
the country.
And we really want to figure out through the planning process and then through the use
of the funds ways that we can really harness the potential of a Lancaster AI hub prepare for the changing changing industry and and ultimately position community members and businesses for success and to grow those economic
opportunities as as we're experiencing this change going back to your question about the Lancaster County Community Fund, they would be serving as the financial manager of the funds of the fiduciary to make sure that we are maintaining and handling these
funds properly and responsibly.
As I spoke about, Lancaster EDC would be playing a strategic role, and after we have the guidance from that that plan from that strategy there still will be decisions made about
the funds and that that's where we've discussed and it is actually spelled out in the community benefits agreement about establishing a committee that's helping to make those decisions what a five-person committee a representative of Carissa Technology Parks a representative of EDC the director of
community planning and economic development that's myself or designee from our department, a representative of the community foundation, and also a community
representative appointed by the mayor and confirmed by city council. One of the things that I wanted to note here is we had a conversation with Carissa Technology Parks when we started the negotiation about the financial contributions, and we did ask them whether they wanted to sincerely be involved in the deployment of these funds and in continued connection and support of the community in the coming years. And they said that is something that they want to do, that they want to participate in. Of course, there's monetary benefits, but there's other non-monetary partnership benefits there as well. And so they did agree and asked to be one of the members and the committee to help make decisions about those funds thank you mr. hamburger I think this will be a question for you what happens if council votes no on this resolution tonight council puts itself and puts the city at risk of these properties being built without getting any of these benefits as a matter of law they have their rights to proceed with land development plans zoning if needed and fight litigation over that but ultimately if they present land development plans that meet the requirements of the ordinance our land our Planning Commission can turn them down but in court they'd be overturned the Planning Commission's role is to enforce the ordinance as written if they supply plans that are compliant then they will meet currently the zoning of
these properties has been established as a permitted use even if a new ordinance were to go in place. I don't think it would be in place in order to be applicable to these properties.
So land development is the last of the and the only real procedural matters where the city's public input comes into play and it's significant. But if they meet the if they meet
the requirements of those of their ordinances, they meet the of law they're going to build the data centers and you won't have any of the benefits built into this agreement and none of the oversight and enforcement
that's in this agreement to be clear correct thank you let's see I had that covers that question my final question for I turn it over to the rest of council does council have the ability to amend this benefit agreement as written we've been told that this is the final version this is the final negotiation it's sort of a we're done we've given you the best we're gonna give you I mean I I can't speak for an owner of what it comes back but what I've been told is no this is it this is the best you're going to get it's a good agreement from their perspective at least that's how they view it and so it becomes council's choice to accept it or not accept it I have one more question actually did the part of the the parties to this agreement the LLC's but we'll say
Carissa Technology Parks is how we started did they were they required or
obligated to enter this agreement in any way no okay thank you I'm gonna open it up to comments and questions from counsel at this time I'm gonna start down here I'm just gonna go right down councillor med Thank You council President thank you solicitor and director Delves my first question is for the solicitor in regards to the agreement can you speak to what happens if the property is sold the agreement provides that any successors in interest to the properties are going to be bound by the agreement thank you and my second question was I understand the two funds being based in economic development and sustainability is there a way for the city to implement some of our affordable housing priorities into these funds I'll turn that over to mr. Dells yeah councillor Ahmed thank you for the question and we did discuss this as a possible priority and ultimately determined that that no this was not the
appropriate source of funds for affordable housing investments as I said
earlier we were really trying to connect the contributions to relevant issues and decided that we really wanted to focus those investments into environment and
sustainability and the economic development because of those natural
nexus points with data centers and AI hub one one thing sure I would just like
to note that's also been quite frankly a requirement of the developers. They've wanted the money to be utilized for things that are related to the project
that they're building. They also have some legal and tax reasons for wanting to make sure that the funds are tied to the type of uses that the data centers actually provide. Councilor Ahmed, the one other thing that I would note is just trying to step back and think about how we're meeting all of our public
policy objectives by investing in these areas using these funds I do think there's an argument to be made that it potentially frees up other funds within the city budget to to tackle affordable housing that's been absolute top
priority for my department top priority for the city administration so that continue will continue to be be the case we we didn't talk any about the permit fees related to the data center construction but I think maybe just to draw a link here one of the same things that we've proposed in the budget is to
fund permitting capacity with data center revenue and I think that that
provides some real benefits related to housing production that's not to say that we're using that there are other subsidies that we use other programs that we draw upon to subsidize the financing of affordable housing but there's also large costs related to the design the really the entitlement
process and the permitting that I think especially is difficult for smaller
organizations and smaller affordable housing projects to sustain thank you and my final question is briefly for the solicitor in regards to the enforcement
and remedies I see that there's cure dates of 30 to 60 days if there was a major breach of the agreement would there be possible injunction within
those cure dates there's nothing here that I can see a major would be they're not using the energy no I mean we'd have to give the 30 year we'd have to give 30 days notice they have to cure within the 30 days or they can get a 30-day extension providing their they've started seeking the remedy providing the
remedy and are in good faith dealing with it but the remedies here I mean the provisions here I don't think there would be anything that a court would
jump at and say predates or takes priority over the notice provisions thank and that concludes my questions thank you for other comments from council councillor Arroyo Thank You council president thank you both for the presentation I really appreciate kind of going step by step of the community benefits agreement and the detail that has gone into this I see a lot of the concerns that have been brought to council addressed in this agreement which is it's good to hear I have a question regarding the e waste and decommissioning process so when we talk about a comprehensive e waste plan can describe what that could look like especially as some of the concerns that have been brought to council is what if had what happens if they walked out through the keys on the roof what would happen and how would the city be responsible if we would be responsible so the city is not responsible for a private property period right so you know we deal with properties that are left vacant many other means and mechanisms if the if they violate code we can then proceed the the e waste and decommissioning plan is really meant to provide for the for the owners to provide a plan for how they intend to
deal with replacement of equipment as it happens it's it's not expected that all of their equipment computer technology you know my kids have taught me that today I get my new iPhone it's already outdated so we know that we know that
commuter computer technology is always changing which means they're going to be updating whether that's chips whether that's other equipment the commissioning
plan is meant to and we will have to approve it provide that they're going to do so in manners that are safe meet this applicable state and federal laws and that they do have a plan in place for if they shut down that being said
enforceability of if they just close shop and disappear that's the challenge
We face with any same as if any other business was to close shop and disappear I think the investment here is pretty significant and there's going to be some lenders at bay That would probably be coming in to sell the property sell the equipment and take care of it long before we would have to And just to be clear that plan will be presented to the city and have to be approved by the city
Yes for each building. Yeah. Thank you. That concludes my question comes president. Thank you counselor colleagues. Thank you. I don't present And thank you both, you know, for the presentation. And who will be monitoring for the CDD operation of the dealer centers to make sure that they are compliant with the regulations in case that, you know, they don't meet? It's really there's no one person that's going to be assigned an obligation to monitor just like any other business that operates or anybody else that uses their property. There are annual reporting requirements that have to be met. They have permit requirements, as Mr. Yates indicated, that they're going to have to meet we obviously will assign somebody to dock it following up and making sure we receive the documents but you know in terms of how we will monitor quite frankly it's through the construction process through the land development process through the inspection process to make sure they're built then the noise testing happens obviously we'll be taking care of making sure that they
can't get their their final certificates of occupancy until they've completed the noise testing so I I don't know if there's any one person but there'll be a
collective effort amongst the city and how often there will be inspections well the city does not going to be inspecting the property outside of the certificate of occupancy once that's issued unless there's some code violation or other reason to do so thank you for the questions thank you very much but I want to go back as a follow-up to that question as we worked on the line we heard about ongoing inspections from the PA Department of Environmental Protection is that those will be ongoing and it sounds like at least annually and on an ongoing basis I don't I don't want to commit to how frequently PA Department
protection will inspect that's a resource driven issue but but the department does take very seriously the permits they issue we're the subject of their permit of several of their permits in other areas and you know they they monitor the reporting we do we get inspected we get audited we get all sorts of things so i'm going to assume that um you know the department will do the same at with the air permits as it
does with the other types of permits that they're responsible for thank you continuing with council comments or questions on this side of the dais counselor diaz thank you president um what specific steps can the that the city is going to take to ensure that the actual owner which be consuming enormous amount of water and energy does not qualify for lerda tax abatement intended for projects that benefit the local community um thank you counselor diaz neither of these properties are eligible for lerda they're not in the lerda zone so they will not they will not have access to those particular tax benefits
Would also add that the statement about the water
Was addressed in the first part of our presentation about the limits 20,000 gallons, which is a fourth of the use Previous at this at this site. We don't need reporting regarding that they're metered. They're paying a water bill to the city We'll know how much water usage they know
thank you and I would also just add that they're in addition to them not being in the looted district there are no other tax incentives that the city is offering
for either of these properties thank you I would like to follow up with a question so they can still apply through the county is that correct or not the way the application process works is they apply through the city and then the application goes to the county tax office we're the first line that determines whether it's eligible or not is the greenfield part of the city or is that falling under the county 216 Greenfield Road yes is within the city
boundaries okay thank you otherwise we wouldn't be talking about it tonight is
that right correct there there is a small portion of the site that stretches into East Lampeter right yeah thank you councilor do you have anything further thank you council Hirsch anything right for the moment I didn't my questions have been answered thank you very much one more okay all right thank you at this time we will move into our public comment on this legislative on this
resolution anyone wishing to make public comment may do so at this time please come up to the microphone you may want to line up if I suspect there will be
many people that wish to do so please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record you'll be asked to do that and again comments are limited to three minutes per speaker good evening and thank you yes Thank You council members and mayor for having this and it's Bill Simonson this November marks my 14th year living in the city your block of residence right sorry I live on 836 Roll Ridge thank you right at the street from the Lancaster rec first off my apologies I had a lot of fire and brimstone prepared and then the CBA came out so I've sort of amended my remarks so if I ramble a little bit my apologies um first let me just say that seeing everybody here tonight uh my undergrad and graduate work was on participant participatory democracy so seeing this many people show up i know um when we participate in good faith even if we disagree it makes our country stronger so i'm hopeful for that um you know so often these days when we turn on the tv or open your phone so you you you look at the newspaper you kind of realize in many ways i think we blew it and in some ways i i kind of think that's the case here um you know we talk a lot about the benefits of ai well we're i think if i can explain some of the frustration in here
and across our country and i think this is going to be an issue in 2026 and in 2028 ai I mean, we're living in a moment here that wasn't of our own choosing.
You know, we are watching tech billionaires sort of steer us into an arms race with China over AGI or ASI. And that makes a lot of us nervous. You know, Dario Armandei was on TV, if you're not familiar. He's the CEO of one of these tech giants. and he recently said that you know within five years time it's quite likely or likely that 50 percent of all entry-level white-collar jobs will be wiped out so you can wonder why some of us are
a little nervous about that you know if you have kids who are getting ready to graduate college i mean these people are going on tv elon and others essentially bragging about the fact that a lot of jobs are going to be lost and no one seems to be able to answer what those will be replaced with um once again to bring up dario because he's in the news a lot he's uh promising 50 billion dollars for the creation of data centers across the u.s and in his own words that's going
to lead to 800 permanent jobs i don't know about anybody else but that doesn't sound like a great
investment to me and you know listen i understand we're in a small city it's hard there are decisions
that need to be made but you know these are and this is a technology that people openly admit you know gregory hinton and others or jeffrey hinton and others who worked for you know chat gpt and google who's left over safety concerns that we don't really know as it gets stronger whether we can control it so i think some of that is born out of our frustration here because this is mr. Simonson thank you thank you good evening your last name Jen for our meeting record Rogers thank you I'm gonna try to I have a lot to say so I'm gonna try to be quick I'm a marketer I'm not anti AI but I I know you guys don't want to talk too much about the zoning but I just want to say that I feel this entire process is very indicative of Trump's America where our representatives do something and then force us to react so I don't really appreciate that that is not how the democratic process works this is clearly
not a warehouse and I don't want that to be forgotten now that we've just moved
on to the CBA I see a lot of money centered language as I said I'm a marketer ideal in language and we're not having the same conversation we can't eat money we can't breathe you know money and we're in a historic community that is very old you know around the founding of our country I don't want to see it destroyed this is a very special place not everybody wants endless development development is not inherently a good word we're not all concerned about two million dollars ten million dollars some of us like living in a smaller community where we feel like we have an impact and not only that to say oh we're gonna give you ten million dollars or act as though that that making this enforceable is somehow a bonus it should be enforceable that shouldn't be a bonus and again you know saying well we're gonna dictate how you use these millions of dollars it's not gonna go to affordable housing it's gonna go to tax breaks which means they're not actually giving us money they're turning around and taking those tax breaks and utilizing it for themselves and I just feel like you guys think we're really gullible and that you can throw a bunch of legal jargon and a lot of millions of dollars towards us and we're gonna go cool this when is this gonna be collaborative it's a community benefit agreement it should be written by the community and this is not satisfactory and it's a lot of the people in here are Democrats and I do not appreciate you know I may are taking a page from Trump's book forcing us to act retroactively and then dipping
on a problem that we are not going to have to face as a community so that's what i have to say
thank you good evening hi taylor raymond 500 block of saint joseph street um so i've spent the last month or two reading up on community benefits agreements what makes a strong one what makes a weak one and i'll say there are a lot of really good things in this i appreciate the work that you've done however it is a community benefits agreement without the community so really it is the mayor's benefits agreement um that's not acceptable to me honestly um the community absolutely should have had a lot more input we should have been told of all of these updates we should have been kept in the loop on the negotiating process um and we weren't we also got the uh the draft of this two days ago as anybody uh in here with a full-time job understands it's really hard to read a 32-page legal document on the evenings and lunch breaks for in two days
and understand what it all entails we need more time i think that you should postpone the vote on this for at least one week and i think that you should put the cba up on engage lancaster
so that people can have input so that people can ask questions and have concerns and suggest things that may have that you all might not have considered all of that aside i have two questions the first is does this hold weight in the part of the greenfield center that is outside of our outside of the city's jurisdiction so does east lampeter uh does the east lampeter part have uh do they also benefit from this and then the second question is who is actually involved in this is it the owners the developers or the tenants or all of the above because i see the owners listed on the agreement and you all keep talking about the developers so which one is it if I could endeavor to answer those questions with the remainder of your time if that would be okay yes Eastland Peter benefit so they were not a party to the agreement but they benefit because they're so close so the environmental and quality of life benefits anyone on the Eastland Peter side of that I would say second part of your question I apologize say that last part again who is actually involved in the agreement is it the developers owners of the tenants the developers and the owners are one in the same the parties to the agreement are the LLC's that have been developed for the management but it's the same parties so the parties of the agreement are the
city and the owners of the property which is to say the developer so the
owners are Carissa the owner is Carissa they've created a standard practice LLC's for each building one in the same okay thank you mm-hmm thank you you can feel free to move that down if you need to great great good evening thank you good evening my name is Theresa Womble and I live at the 200 block of East Orange Street and I'm in addition to being a resident of Lancaster City I also am a leader at Armstrong World Industries so I'm here tonight in support of the CBA and the growth that can come from these investments as many of you know Armstrong has been a major manufacturer and employee employer in Lancaster county for over 100 years and currently we have about 1 000 employees in this area who are interested in seeing growth continue to happen so the investments that are being made by the cba will benefit our company and our employees and their families in addition armstrong is happy bdb supplying product that go into these projects which will support our employee base as well as the investments we can make back into the community so i appreciate the work that the city council and the mayor have done to put together a creative solution that i think is a great opportunity almost unique for the city to continue growth thank you thank you good evening
good evening my name is daryl legacy i live in the 100 block of north mary street
and i also want to thank the council for the work that they've done on this i know this is a very complicated project um i do have a few questions one is it feels like this is a pay to pollute agreement it feels like they are just going to pay the 20 million dollars and say oh well we couldn't get to 100 energy and there's nothing stopping them from doing that um this is the cost of doing business. This is like a rounding error on their budget. I think another problem with that is while this is a rounding error for them, it also is a super volatile sector right now. I just was looking and Corweave, which I know is not Carissa, but Corweave, which is going to be using at least one of these buildings, has lost almost, I think it's like 35% of their stock since June, their stock price. So these companies are just going to be promising all of this money, promising all this revenue and then what happens when they go out of business and throw the keys on the roof as we heard we're stuck with this vacant building I think that's a big problem and I think it's something that needs to be addressed I think we should not be pre-complying with this idea that the zoning agreement does not apply retroactively I realize that that is I'm sure the biggest demand that they have I'm sure they will not sign this agreement without that but I think that's something to consider if it is so important to them they must think there's at least a chance that this could be retroactive. If there was no chance, they would just say, whatever, we don't care. Legally, we're going to win. So I think that's something that we should be concerned about. I think also a bad deal could be worse than no deal. I'm not convinced that this is a bad deal yet, but I think we should at least consider the possibility. I also think there's something to be gained by telling these companies that we are not open for their business. Yes, there's some
risk. It's possible that if we don't sign this agreement, they build anyway, they win the court
case, and they just pollute and do whatever they want. Now, they're already bound by the state and federal laws, though I really appreciate them agreeing that they will be bound by the laws. So I think it's potentially in our benefit to just say, no, we're not going to do that. Then we gum up the works. We do everything we can to slow down their construction. We do everything to make it uncomfortable for them. And then all of us here, we go protest. We protest. We block construction. We do everything it takes to slow this down. They don't want that. They want us to just say, oh, well, I guess it's the best we could get. I don't think that's a good idea. and then lastly I would love to know if any members of the city of the city government and or the mayor signed an NDA and now I know the nature of NDAs are that you're not gonna say yes I signed an NDA but whether it's here or in public I'm gonna take anything other than a resounding no as yes that you did and I think that is a huge problem there was a huge article that just came out saying they're all requiring city officials to sign NDAs and then to block FOIA requests that is a huge problem and I would feel much more trust I would have much more trust if I knew for sure that that did not happen with anyone here including the zoning director who just single-handedly approved this thank you no I was not asked to sign an NDA I'll allow any member of council who wishes to to make no I did not sign an NDA I did not sign an NDA I was asked I i did not sign an nda i did not sign an nda at all i did not sign an nda i did not sign an nda thank you good evening good evening my name is eric souder i'm from east petersburg i am the founder of regional local climate organization i'd like to thank the city for your work on this it's a very thoughtful document as has been mentioned i believe there are numerous impacts like land use water consumption and on-site emissions that could actually be significantly worse if these data centers were not located adjacent to the city so that is one concern that i have if this were somewhere else but my primary focus is energy the through the greenhouse gas inventory that regional developed for the county we can show that the two data centers will use a combined electricity consumption that's 10 times that of the city and 82 percent of the entire County combined and this is really enormous and unprecedented so in light of that I'd like to highlight several elements of the CBA where I see the greatest opportunity for us to make progress toward a resilient Lancaster moving forward first the CBA places much of the work within the context of the city's climate action plan I know there's been real interest in seeing the city expand this to a community climate action plan this is necessary to develop up climate strategy that covers all lancaster residents and in addition to city operations second i'm glad that there's a thermal heat mitigation plan required in section 4.4 i really encourage the city to explore opportunities here fully there's several examples of data centers especially in europe that are using waste heat in district loops to heat buildings as i discussed this idea across the community i learned of earlier efforts to investigate a central heating plant at F&M Park City and the hospital combined so it shows that there's been real interest from the community to explore things like this and shuttle heat quite the distance so I think there are real possibilities there that we need to explore 300 megawatts in as energy is 300 megawatts out as heat and we have an opportunity to use that third I'm encouraged by the 100% renewables commitment but it also matters where where that energy comes from. You could imagine a forest being cut down
to install solar and satisfy the requirement.
So I'd like us to explore creative collaborations with the tenants to purchase energy in an escalating manner that helped us to deploy local renewables through that. You can imagine our phones, like Carrier will give us the phone to lock us into those ongoing payments. The real value here is that energy. And I'd look to creative ways that we can use this moment do the energy and renewables deployment that we need to buffer our community from rising electric costs so to me this really comes down to our creativity and imagination if this is happening to use this moment to be as transformative as we can thanks thank you good evening hi my name is emily baldies i live at the 100 block of north mary street i just wanted to briefly thank the council members for their contributions this evening also city solicitor and the experts that information was very helpful i have some residual concerns i think we've heard a lot of really valid concerns from other commentators so i'm just going to focus on air quality for a minute in the cba that was shared with us air quality is addressed in a single paragraph in section 3.2 that essentially states that the ai hubs will comply with state and federal emissions laws and well i'm glad to know that ai hub owners are willing to not break the law this still feels woefully insufficient to me and so while we're considering whether this version of the agreement is the best path forward i would also like to suggest that council consider potential public health costs especially around air pollution which ai data centers have been proven to produce. I have concerns about the fact that the backup generators, I learned this evening, there are going to be 176 of those, that those generators directly release harmful air pollutants like nitrogen oxides. There are also a significant amount of pollutants created by the extra energy usage that AI data centers produce. And those types of air pollution, we all know, contribute to diseases like asthma, lung cancer, heart attacks, etc. As I was researching this particular issue in the couple of days that we had after the CBA came out, I found a couple of studies, one of which was conducted by scientists at Caltech and UC Riverside, and they warn of tremendous public health costs that attend air pollution increases, like the types that we're talking about here they found that the amount of electricity needed to train a large language model produced the amount of air pollution equivalent to more than 10,000 round trips by car from LA to New York City they estimate that national public health costs national to be clear from these diseases caused by air pollution and aggravated by data centers will be around 20 billion by 2030 if You'd prefer an example closer to home. They talked about the AI data centers in Northern, Virginia those create air pollution that drifts into Pennsylvania, Maryland, New York, New Jersey, Delaware and creates regional are estimated to create regional public health costs of between 190 and 260 million dollars per year and that can increase if those centers are operating at maximum permitted levels all of which is to say The potential benefits to the city as provided and negotiated in the CBA sound like a lot of money But the potential costs also sound Tremendous and so I hope that as we're considering this City Council will keep the cost benefit in mind. Thank you Feel free to move that to wherever you need. Good evening Good evening. My name is Jamie Morrison. I am the Vice President and General Manager of LV Concrete. Our office is at 1287 Loop Road in Lancaster City, and we were lucky enough to do the foundation package in Building 1. We have 44 employees. 60% of them are residents of Lancaster County. The rest of them are in central PA, so they are benefiting directly for the work that we were able to obtain. We think this is a great reuse of brownfield sites, and it gives our employees work to do locally, and a lot of times, construction work slows down in the winter, and this is an opportunity for all our employees to benefit and make a good living close to home. So I appreciate everybody's work in this, and I support it.
Thank you.
Good evening. Good evening. Jordan Farrell, East Petersburg.
My company is IREX, right across the street here, over on Lime Street. We are a specialty contracting company. We employ around 100 employees in the local community here. And another thing is I've been working with, involved with EDC, Finance Corporation, for the last, since 2019. I say these things to illustrate how involved in the community and the well-being of the
community, economic well-being of the community.
I'm here to express support for the data center and the community benefit agreement. This project represents a meaningful investment to the community's long-term well-being. It will transform two vacant industrial buildings into modern facilities that are going to provide thousands of construction jobs and hundreds of permit jobs to the community as was previously mentioned it will help to employ people here locally that will be able to have construction jobs close to home I respectfully urge council to approve the community benefits agreement allowing this project to move forward and bring with it the opportunity to advance the economic health of our
community thank you thank you good evening my name is Shawn was Nikki and I live my address is in Lancaster but I don't live in Lancaster I live closer to
Landisville actually I hate this this is about I mean I don't like the data centers too but I don't like speaking publicly I'm saying it's a little bit
it's a little bit north of getting a root canal but this is really important and I want to talk about it because I think it's gonna drastically affect
Lancaster City and Lancaster County for years to come so again like everybody has said Thank You council for working on this for making something out of nothing and having things having that there be concrete benefits but as has been said the community got to look at this on on Tuesday and it's Thursday and
if it is this important and if it is this this big I think the community deserves more time to review it and make suggestions if there could be that allowance to be made that would be great I don't as a I don't know as a parent of
two kids I don't appreciate somebody going through a long presentation of all the benefits and then saying at the end if you say no you get nothing that feels not like they wish to be invested in the community that they wish to say take this so that we can take whatever we want it doesn't feel like a partnership without a more time obviously I only have a couple of things to say but I did want to say that I would very much like to have nuclear energy stricken from the clean energy list that's on there as a clean energy LPE units 1 & 2 are mentioned in article 8 for the financial agreements but not LPW there's nothing in there about that and I don't know if this is a legally binding document if they're not in there if they can just go out on that the letter of credit can be substituted for a company of a hundred million dollars net worth please get rid of that uh as somebody has mentioned core weave has lost 40 of its stock valuation in the last six months um that is that is not a very uh good idea i feel like and uh there's new info coming out all the time we just got to see something from the lancaster county planning commission that has a lot of new ideas and recommendations and we'd love to be able to take that into account as a community thank you thank you good evening evening thank you for the opportunity to speak
this evening jeremy young i'm a city resident but here tonight i'm here on behalf of the organization i work for lancaster city alliance one of several economic development focused organizations
including economic development company of lancaster county we have a representative here tonight from that organization the lancaster chamber and socket development corporation We collectively wrote a letter to council, and hopefully you received that letter dated yesterday, November 19th, in support of the Community Benefits Agreement.
And if you don't mind, for the record, I'll just paraphrase that letter for everyone here tonight.
Together, we as economic development organizations focused on the city and the county support the adoption of the Lancaster AI Hub Community Benefits Agreement. over the past several weeks we've listened carefully to residents concerns we met with the carissa technologies team and city staff to understand the project and this agreement in particular in detail those conversations have given us confidence that if implemented and monitored with care this community benefits agreement can channel a private investment toward clear enforceable benefits for the residents of lancaster we recognize environmental impacts are a major concern and very rightfully so but we see this agreement as a tool that puts expectations mitigation measures and accountability in writing rather than leaving them to chance and that's really key we really feel that this agreement puts us in the best and strongest possible place and in a better place than where we would be if we did not have an agreement just as importantly the agreement is structured to deliver community-centered outcomes especially those tied to economic development right here in the city of lancaster including training and upskilling for city residents support for entrepreneurs and small businesses adapting an ai enabled economy a sustainability fund to advance local priorities and expanded access to ai tools and education so that lancaster can remain competitive for all these reasons we
respectfully urge you to approve the community benefits agreement and we are here to support you
thank you for your time and consideration thank you good evening tony dastro 700 block new holland
avenue um mr arcolio couldn't be here tonight so on his behalf i just want to make a note before
my comment that he wants it noted the absence of any mention of harrisburg pike or lpw in section 8 of the cba regarding the contribution to lccf and the community and the city community funds So let me see if I can bring some pizzazz here. When I read this agenda initially, my first reaction was, like, I thought of the April Fool's joke when they were saying we're going to do AR reality over at the garage over there.
Because, like, how do we go from data center to innovation hub?
Why are we dressing this up now all of a sudden? I'll tell you why. It's because it's clear we're in the middle of a negotiation.
It's very clear we're in the middle of a negotiation. My biggest problem with moving forward with this agreement is the pending litigation, as it was mentioned earlier.
There is pending litigation on this issue, and the public is actively fighting whether or not this use is permitted. And I think the city is jumping on the middle of the train tracks. There is something else going on, and the city should not jump on the middle of the train tracks.
We need to let it carry through. Frank should have his day at the Zoning Hearing Board, as well as anyone else who wants to be a party to that. We deserve to have that heard through on appeal. and that appeal can be appealed
so this is not just a once and done thing
we are at the beginning of potentially a very long process and the public is not content
with what's currently been presented to us we should not be suddenly going hey why are we suddenly the welcoming city to data centers like what's happening and to the note of all the construction jobs and the sentiments in the room the people who have come in support of those positions I think a majority of the people in this room want to see you get jobs but for housing projects we want to talk about housing projects in developing a community that way the city talks about our limitations and what we can and can't do but we haven't discussed the most radical of all things the city can do with property eminent domain to see our community goals met and now I'm not suggesting here today let's make an offer but I am saying we're in the middle of a negotiation and if we're in the middle of negotiation I don't know where this is all gonna pan out but if we're here I'd rather have have one data center than two so if we can put an absolute stop to the second one at all that's a great thing so we need to amend the zoning amendment to exclude the use from the central manufacturing zone because that puts a stop to number two right then and there because they haven't submitted land development we need y'all fighting for us and we need you to table this i'm not saying don't approve it i'm not saying i can't be convinced that this is this is some parts of can be enacted but i am saying table this and do not put this in writing and hold us to this standard wait because we're winning thank you good evening good evening uh john benvenuto uh live 800 block of north reservoir street um i think of one word that's that when i listen to people speaking here tonight and that is trust the community has to feel trust in you and in what you decide supposedly to do for us we've been presented as has been mentioned tuesday afternoon this was published and some of us have studied it and read it and and done the best we could with all the where force and as to what uh but trust is a major thing it's a complex multi-faceted document committing us for years in this community and of concern to all citizens of lancaster their well-being and welfare and trust is the apparent lack of representation in measuring and certifying some of these provisions now it's just passed off like a momentary comment that once a year you're allowed to contest the noise at this facility. So, excuse me, once every two years. So there are definite limitations put on yourself and ourselves to live with this in detail and in the general construction as some people have noted already. and citizens should be represented by a strong third party perhaps a city planning commission or some created commission that could certify every measurement that is made in all of the elements for this project not take the submission of paperwork 30 pages 50 pages 100 i don't care what but we need someone to help safeguard ourselves in this whole process as it plays out 10 20 years from now and i do think decommissioning is an issue that ought to be in the back of people's minds thank you very much thank you good evening good evening tim stooler 800 block of george street uh first of all regarding the agreement in general uh it seems like uh number one uh city has identified what appear to be the main uh negative externalities and is taking action to ensure that there are enforceable ways to mitigate those that's encouraging that's very good uh also appreciate uh the mayor and i think uh mr handworker confirming um no uh tax incentives no larda i attended tuesday's meeting in which we talked about the budget city parentally faces difficult budgets these are large properties that are going to have high property values that should serve to protect some of our lowest income residents if we have that additional revenue less need for property tax increases that has to serve folks on fixed incomes and again lower income residents two questions and one comment uh the questions number one uh with regard to the environmental commitments i would hope that those are pegged to the law as it exists today it certainly seems like the federal government has some interest in weakening clean air and water laws i would not want that to be an excuse for the data center to you know wend from what it originally committed to second there's a reference to a decommissioning plan uh does that include a bond or some uh financial commitment to ensure that that decommissioning can take place as far as my comment this is a bit of a nitpick but i object to the idea of devoting 250 000 to a strategic plan for using the economic development fund i would remind city council we did our future lancaster that was approved just at the end of 2023 lancaster city alliance is doing building on strength we have the edc we have the lancaster chamber we have the department of neighborhood engagement that engage the
community in my view we've done an awful lot of economic planning yes data centers are somewhat
different but in general we know what we want we want good jobs we want a growing economy want to
support our small business i don't see why we need to spend 250 000 to look once again at how to
do that thank you thank you good evening hi i'm ro potter of i never get this right but i'm on 67 south franklin street i don't know if that's the hundred block or the six zero block exactly it just doesn't make sense anyway anyway this is not my first meeting up here i do see some first-time faces though some of them are susan ties telling us to be okay with what's happening even though they're not being clear about really anything i've gone to this type
of meeting they had an ai summit down at the ware center about last week and the number one thread
that i've noticed throughout all this is that it's fucking vague there's nothing that is just saying like hey right out in the open this is our plan this is what we're doing it all has to look like technological mumbo jumbo and it's just supposed to go over the average person's mind like who who wants to be here protesting this shit at eight o'clock at night on a thursday i got to be up at four in the morning tomorrow. I don't want to do this. And yet we have suits and ties out here telling us to be okay. And what? Pass our time, twiddle our thumbs, and what else? It just doesn't make any sense to me. I'm sorry. I don't like being born into a city. You know, I didn't really have much of a pick. We're all put here for one way or another unless you moved in. But anyways, I really, really don't like when people come into our city, tell us what to feel, how to feel and what to do about it and then that's it we don't get any decisions on it it doesn't make any sense to me the amount of times that people come out and protest this thing and said we want a different approach or a different you know and we're all at the height of the ai bubble too this thing could pop in any month from now i don't know if you pay attention and they don't want you to but i think it's sam altman open ai guy or someone running nvidia just traded all their fucking stock what is that going to thank you peter teal someone just said it what does that tell you this is a bubble waiting the burst and you know why because it's not sustainable we're sitting here talking about currently making construction jobs currently boosting the economy
what is the long term are we are we dumb what is the long term think on the long term your air
your water your they're already complaining about birth rates so what's next they fuck our air up we can't produce i'm sorry if i'm using profanity i can't but it just is so short-sighted and of course it's about money of course it's about businesses it's never about the people when you're talking about building warehouses and all this other stuff when we walk by the same potholes that have been here longer than i've been alive they don't make any sense at all and i know y'all doing your best i see all the time really and you just got elected mayor so i hope you're equipped for this but for real they're doing their best and we're trying to communicate but really it's the people that come out and say, hey, be okay with it or else. What does that mean? Because I'd rather find out what else means rather than letting them do whatever with our city.
It doesn't make any sense. Thank you. Good evening. Hi. My name is Nancy Griffith. I live on the zero block of South Lyme.
So I was wondering if there's ever been an assessment done of property values in cities that already have existing data centers. if that analysis has been done I will tell you I just recently moved to Lancaster Lancaster sorry I just pronounced it wrong you can tell go on that's okay for a certain quality of life that I was hoping to get here had I
known that these data centers were in progress I never would have bought a
home here never would have moved here so you can imagine my frustration if these data centers come to fruition I'm leaving getting out of here thanks thank you good evening I love on the 800 block of 3rd Street and I'm just gonna speak
to some stuff that hasn't been spoken to and that I don't think anybody's gonna
speak to but I'm gonna start with my favorite chant which says earth my body water my blood air my breath and fire my spirit the animals who live at Longs Park are my brothers and sisters I'm there in sacred community with all of us
and there are community members here too that I feel like aren't being represented
there's a specific part of the CBA that I forgot to write down the numbers and letters but it says that there's like certain residential zones and certain park zones this is in regards to the noise and about the nighttime and I'm sure you can find it but it talks about how the park zones have different rules for the resident zones and that there's different rules at nighttime for the noise and so I want to talk about the animals who live in the park and who are going to be affected by the nighttime noise and how important how incredibly important those animals lives as individuals and families who have homes here in our city and share this land with us how important they are that they also are healthy and well trees the same thing goes for the trees there's a section 8 I wrote down four point six point two where it says integrate native species it doesn't say that they need to use all native species and there's absolutely no reason why you wouldn't make them use all native species there's just no excuse for not having that in the language at all there's plenty of local companies it's super easy to have all native plants there's there's no excuse for not having that language in there just into integrate native is all it says um and then the other two chunks um that are concerning
to me i mean all of this is concerning to me and i'll be there with a sign no matter if this gets signed or not or whatever happens um i agree with so many of the other things that were said but
the other two chunks that stick out to me is um you know this grandfathered in thing that's happening with the proposed zoning ordinance and hearing that like there's no development plan in place for building three specifically i'm wondering like if there's no plan in place now why are we giving them two years they're not grandfathers they haven't even been born yet
um and the thing that somebody else said about how the city can only report or complain about
the noise once every two years is blasphemy i can't even believe that we should be able to complain whenever we want thank you thank you good evening good evening my name is kevin bachelor uh 200 block of north charlotte street i just wanted to say a couple things I think it's clear from the energy in this room that nobody likes a bully and as we heard very plainly when our solicitor was asked what happens if we don't accept this agreement Carissa technology is a bully they are a bully dressed up like a partner please don't be complicit in the bullying of our city thank you good evening good evening my name is Matthew Barden 800 block of North Prince there are a lot of things I want to touch on that have been touched
on here already how toothless our ability to actually inspect that they
are meeting these requirements is we're relying on self reporting from a corporation I want to I want to let that sit for a minute we're relying on self reporting we can talk about the sustainability of the jobs it claims to create these are short-term jobs these aren't even in fact it the large portion of these aren't jobs they're creating they're creating work for those jobs and somebody else said we can find better places for that work elsewhere that mean more to our community we could talk about the health cost these we can talk about the fact that corporations skirt fines because it as it was said it was a
fraction of their actual worth we can talk about the fact that all of this has been done without community engagement this isn't a community benefits
agreement this is a hostage negotiation we've seen a number of cities across this entire country push back on these data centers that are being forced on
them and win and i ask why not us why are you treating this like a foregone conclusion that
we have to settle for this we don't we can win this and we deserve to win this we don't deserve to have one one zoning permit change everyone's lives in in this city in this community we can
win this and we deserve it and we deserve you to continue to fight for us instead of accepting this
toothless argument agreement excuse me thank you good evening good evening my name is baruch dewar i'm a 35-year resident of the city live in the thousand block of west clay street just a couple of points here that were raised some of which would be nice to hear answers to before you vote and i was not a party to the beginnings of this process but it appears to me as the first time that i've been exposed to this is this is a classic case of it may not be what you did it's how it's done you know and i was a chief counsel of a pennsylvania state agency for eight years uh worked in government for a long time worked for several governors um under the office of general counsel um you know uh to which is the agency that staffs all the attorneys and all the the state agencies. And that is the one lesson that I probably had driven home to me over and over and over again as a government lawyer attempting to pull off something like this. Great work being done here. Excellent work being done here. But you can't get past the concept of it may not be what was done. It's how you did it or how it was done. And I'm just seeing a room of people here who are driving that point home in spades you know this is clear there is clearly though as somebody mentioned trust whatever whatever was the precursor that led us all to here to this today today clearly there has been an issue of broken trust at this point and again you can't say it enough times it may not be what is the end result but it's how it was done that you know breaks that trust and creates problems that you know can last for you know quite a long time with your constituency so that's just my experience for a long time and you know in government service my other question which is this is the one I would kind of like to get an answer to is I'm not sure
I understand this ten-year power purchase agreement and then after ten years that's it there's no more strings attached to the type of energy that's
being used i mean i understand if that is just the take it or leave it position that they have put on the table then sometimes you may have to leave it because i really don't understand the logic of 10 years and then no more concern no more requirements why why would you do that to somebody who clearly is expressing the intent to put tens of millions of dollars into something and to be there for decades potentially why 10 years and then stop that just makes no sense to me so another small point these 176 generators could have all been required to be powered by biodiesel not petroleum diesel and you know pennsylvania is the only state in the country that has a biodiesel
mandate in our you know diesel that is dispensed at the pump um and we stuck our neck out on that one and we're not even a producer of biodiesel thank you but excuse me thank you 10 the 10-year
issued address thank you good evening good evening my name is charlotte altmer i live on the 200 block of north charlotte street you're gonna have to hear the whole thing some of it's a repeat of what others have said but i don't know how to simplify it on the fly so you're gonna have to stick with me for the whole of this i'll start by voicing an objection to the background point
a in the cba quote to unlock productivity and innovation gains this is debatable and brings
me to my most macro concern and that is the role lancaster is playing in supporting an industry that is grossly unregulated and whose preeminent experts agree poses existential risk to humanity and in the nearer term is positioned to take away jobs from human beings i am pro innovation and growth but i desire to have that innovation and growth be values driven and well considered the rush to get in on ai boom is naive and risky and i fail to see how it supports the city's own plan the comprehensive plan that's been referenced tonight i want to highlight the dollars represented in the cba the proposed lancaster county community foundation being funded in the amount of 20 million dollars as a percentage of this project doesn't scratch a quarter of a percent this sounds like a lot of money but it's not it's not it's 0.2 percent of the project The Sustainable Development and Clean Energy Fund introduced lands like a farce, the idea that we're going to turn a blind eye to known truths in favor of nice-sounding commitments. Data centers are ravenous for limited resources such as water and electric. If you look at the direct and indirect emissions of a data center, you see the issue. Across the organization's entire value chain, you get into troubling truths. The manufacturing of semiconductors and required refrigerants used in data centers are full of forever chemicals which wreak havoc on the sites in which they are manufactured and will eventually wreak havoc on the sites where they are disposed of. Data centers growing across the U.S. will require 22 percent more grid power by the end of 25 and on and on and on. We know this. While the community benefits agreement is asking for clean energy, I think it's important to acknowledge the massive demand for electricity across this sector is problematic, period. Just yesterday and today, WGL, LNP talking about PPNL bringing forward a rate hike right it's a problem i seeing as the community didn't have a say in this work prior to this approval and commencement of the work trust has been broken and i again asked the city council how do you plan to restore trust with the residents that you are meant to represent and serve a recommendation is to deeply listen to what's being shared in tonight's special meeting show humility show patience and ensure the concerns raised tonight are appropriately considered before you authorize and approve the cba beyond the fundamental objection i have to the data center in lancaster i will call out a few specifics in the cba itself section 7.1 transparency is key annual reporting should include third-party noise reporting water use and third-party water quality reports electric use is outlined and a third-party air quality report if the environmental concerns have all been addressed as the agreement suggests show us that your third party audits we've reached three minutes thank you very much good evening good evening my name is Jerry Clase I want to make sure I'm not violating protocol I do not live in Lancaster City that's just fine East Enfield 1352 Jasmine Lane East Enfield I have a couple questions it's about energy okay I know you can't tell us what they will be paying for um electricity but can you publish some indication whether it's 50 90 80 of what the typical resident would pay i would not be happy if i found out that we're subsidizing half of their energy costs because they're paying with 50 of what i am uh have you done a study uh that would show what the projected energy costs would be going out for the next five ten years one with the data center using all the power they do and number two without the energy that the data center would be using i think the numbers are going to be pretty staggering on what the rates are going to uh happen to the citizens of this fine city and thirdly um have they talked at all about uh fusion nuclear power uh i would i know it's five to ten years out but it's something that i think really needs to be discussed uh and it could bring some real benefits to the community of lancaster thank you thank you good evening good evening hi thank you guys for being here and all the work that's done my name is francis musselman i'm on the 500 block of west chestnut street um i understand that the agree i understand today that the agreement text in front of you is the final and today's vote is yes or no with no amendments is that right that's correct i also understand that the 20 million dollars has already been conceptually allocated so a no vote is being framed as leaving that money on the table my concern is that in section 10.1 it states that we're locking Lancaster into a 20-year industrial agreement is it a 20-year industrial agreement have we been talking about the limit especially with the 10-year energy deal so you have a 10-year energy deal but then we're in a 20-year industrial agreement in one of the fastest changing sectors on earth i was at the open house talking to the gensler architects and they said that in within a year they have to go and redesign some of the buildings because it's moving so quickly so this agreement will last until 2045. is that right do we know we didn't talk about the limit so the most of the money is going to be arriving in the first three years and then the impacts are going to continue for 20 years the risks are long term and the leverage is short term if you choose to vote yes i'm asking you to pair that vote with a concrete commitment on implementing number one creating a formal community oversight body to track this agreement including noise diesel use energy mix and how the 20 million is actually spent require public number two require public reporting at least annually or like quarterly actually on key metrics and energy use clean energy share generator testing noise levels and finally open up a 20 million dollar plan to generally genuinely get public input not just a pre-decided list that part i think is the one that hurts the most but it's 20 years and i think that that should also be reason to pause because it just feels like a very long time thank you good evening hello my name is pat eichmann and i do not live in this city either
i wish i did right now i live less than a mile from the greenfield data center
and i just want to ask the people in here tonight that are supporting this project would they want to live have the data center in their backyard would they be okay with that um i doubt it and i ask you to for the harrisburg center do you want to take your children out to longs park
knowing there are all kinds of air particles floating around the air and poisonous uh
not nitro oxides or whatever floating around i don't think you want to do that do you want to shop at Wegmans with all this pollution and water pollution out there I don't think so and I just want to reiterate that these the core we've data center is their stock has tumbled they are highly highly leveraged it's like a house of cards there's a it's called circular financing there are so many privately private equity firms in this financing you pull one card out and that whole house could crash so they are highly leveraged and if you're thinking of your 20 million dollars if they go bankrupt your 20 million dollars is gone and that might not be too far away because sam altman the ceo of open ai i read the article he did agree that we are going to be in an ai bubble and it's going to pop so i just want to i'll leave that out there Thank you. Good evening. Good evening, councillors. My name is Ezra Rothman. I lead
EDC Lancaster County, the county's lead economic development organization,
also a resident of Lancaster City, 100 block of North Pine Street. I've made my support and complemented the city's efforts on this CBA publicly several times in addition to the letter
that we submitted. So I do want to take a couple minutes to very quickly address an element of our past our present and our future as it relates to this project regarding our
past this data center is not replacing a clean use in our community this was previously an active industrial use that operated 24 7 with heavy truck traffic with emissions and with significantly higher water usage so I do think that we need to be clear about that as we talk about the past uses and the past impacts of this site on our community. Let me talk about the present. I love living in
Lancaster County because of the opportunities I have here. I have opportunities to have a well-paying job and live in a community that I think is accessible. My wife and I can walk to restaurants and I can quickly also get out and enjoy the wonderful environmental amenities that we have in
this community. And a big part of that, especially the economic side, is the diversity of our economy in Lancaster County and that leads to a strong vibrant and resilient economy that also leads me to the future we have an opportunity here to take AI and high tech which is objectively part of our future and bake that into our community that comes with innovation that comes with jobs that comes with money to support us as a community pipelining
residents into those future jobs i'm excited by that opportunity i'm also excited by the opportunity to make further investments in our outdoor resources and amenities in this community
because they absolutely do contribute to our quality of life and economy so i'll reiterate my support for the cba and the commitment of edc lancaster county to continue to support the city and the administration to make sure that this continues to be done the right way thank you thank you good evening good evening uh pam smith i'm gonna claim 750 east king street as my residence since i spend so much time there as the executive vice president at thaddeus stevens college um i just wanted to share a little bit this evening a little bit different spin on all of the comments i've spent the last 20 years in the lancaster city community doing community mobilizing work i think there's a lot of really good points that have been brought up tonight about the process that's involved in that and what can be said for how folks are engaged in that so I wanted to share just a little bit of my experience with this process and the college from the beginning of the conversations around the AI Center started out with a lot of skepticism in our behind closed doors conversations but when you think about what we do as an institution we're a two-year Technical College we have the highest enrollment we've ever had with close to 1,500 students we have 24 programs many of which are connected directly to the work that will be happening whether it's in the preparation of the site looking at heavy construction those kinds of things all the way through the types of services and supports that will be provided there so for us this is a much bigger conversation with a lot of really hard questions that we did ask we had the opportunity to engage I hosted some folks from teresa on-site at campus we went to all of our locations they engage with our students and our faculty and asked really good questions about how we're preparing the workforce what they could be doing to better support what this community needs we talked a lot about what makes lancaster unique and why it thrives the way it does we are not the places that they've talked about that they've they want us to go visit all the other locations they've been we're lancaster we talked with that about what that meant started with them pronouncing it correctly which you heard about tonight but also goes to what makes the fabric of this community and we had a really really great opportunity to engage in conversation around that so for us we want to just make sure that we're advocating for the best opportunities for our students students are graduating right now with 18 job opportunities every time they walk across the stage and we want to make sure that we continue those opportunities for our students in this this community and that we don't lag behind in creating prosperity for them earning family thriving wages and contributing to this community thank you good evening I'm a college student and I would have much rather spent this time studying for my finals but this is very concerning that you just basically are saying they basically said take this deal or else there's the zoning issues to talk about it's AI is objectively bad people like to say it's a tool it has uses it's bad for learning it's bad for the environment it's bad for jobs I'm bad at public speaking so I sound like I'm gonna cry I also wanted to bring up there's no gift ban in Pennsylvania so how are we sure you guys are not getting money from billionaires who are incentivized to build these data centers like it's a concern of course you don't expect your local city council to be like bringing in a million dollar gift from one of these people I'm sure I'm sure we would be able to tell if you got uber rich you guys are not making a ton of money either but um it's a concern that um these big companies are buying out they're buying out the government as a whole as we see in the federal government but on the state level and the city level it's concerning um that that you have to vote now when we only had two days to review this I had homework I could not spend 32 pages reading read all those pages when I had assignments due um so I think from a tech college she might be saying that but I go to Millersville. I'm an art education student. It is scary what is going to happen. I had more I was going to say but I kind of forgot it. But yeah I just I think objectively AI is bad and you should not just like bend to this person. I thought nobody liked solicitors so I don't know like I don't think you should just automatically bend to them and where they say do this or else because we should be fighting it um and i've only lived here for three years if this gets built i'm going to move away i don't want to live near this thank you as soon as we have reached the end of the public comment period i want to thank everybody who spoke this evening and yes public speaking can be tricky and i appreciate everyone um okay we have a motion and a second at hand for this resolution I think we can now call for the vote for that councillors if you have any additional comments does any other councils have additional comments before we would take that vote thank you mr. Harris if you would please call the vote yes madam president mr. men ah mr. Roya aye mr. Cleese aye miss Craig all right miss Diaz no mr. Hirsch hi president Baker thank you I just want to make a brief comment before I vote for me monetary commitments have always been and will be secondary to environmental and quality of life provisions and commitments so I'm only going to speak
about that I'm uncomfortable moving forward in this process without this agreement the level of commitment and oversight is beyond zoning enforcement which is usually
the only teeth we have as municipal government it does not give any tax credits or benefits to the developer it addresses concerns that we have been hearing at council from members of our community and that we have had ourselves for months people have mentioned leaving money on the table but i don't want to leave these provisions or oversights on the table either aye we have reached the conclusion of our agenda this evening uh counselors i'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second the motion and second all in